<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>thebouv - homelab</title><link href="https://thebouv.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://thebouv.com/feeds/homelab.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://thebouv.com/</id><updated>2021-05-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>My thoughts on Amazon Sidewalk</title><link href="https://thebouv.com/my-thoughts-on-amazon-sidewalk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Anthony Bouvier</name></author><id>tag:thebouv.com,2021-05-15:/my-thoughts-on-amazon-sidewalk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My brief thoughts on Amazon Sidewalk and why I'm ditching Alexa hardware&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I originally posted these thoughts on &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/thebouv"&gt;my LinkedIn profile&lt;/a&gt; but wanted to revisit here as well. It is not an in-depth technical analysis. Just a bit of a rant and declaration. A future post with more geeky thoughts is in order for sure. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First the announcement release about &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Amazon-Sidewalk/b?node=21328123011"&gt;Amazon Sidewalk&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon did discuss this before and I remember reading about it on Hacker News or some other aggregate site a few months ago. This is still a terrible, terrible idea and I'll definitely be making sure to disable anything that has Sidewalk implemented. Because rest assured that even though you did the right thing and didn't connect your SmartTV to your home network, Sidewalk will eventually make its way into non-Amazon made products and spread it. That's the goal and one can only imagine the impact of all those devices constantly chatting and &lt;em&gt;sharing information&lt;/em&gt;. That's the real scary part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is my network. That I designed and paid for. It is my internet connection that I pay for. I do NOT want to share even a single packet of information on my network without my explicit permission. Creating this shadow network is complete and total bull crap. And in a month of usage the release above says it is capped aet 500MB. It shouldn't even be a single byte!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shame on you Amazon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is exactly why I'm tossing out my Alexa and building my own voice assistant where I own all the data. So look out for another experiment soon. This now bumps up in priority. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="homelab"></category><category term="homelab"></category><category term="iot"></category></entry><entry><title>First rack for my homelab</title><link href="https://thebouv.com/first-rack-for-my-homelab.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Anthony Bouvier</name></author><id>tag:thebouv.com,2021-03-20:/first-rack-for-my-homelab.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My first open rack for the homelab and the initial equipment I've put in it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="home lab open rack with new Unifi equipment" src="images/homelab-not-pretty-yet.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It ain’t pretty yet but it’s a start and it’s been mostly fun so far!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say mostly fun because running cables in a home from 1914 is a pain in the behind. A lot of plaster and lath walls makes it a challenge and though I haven't had to mess with it too much, I've been doing some planning after getting this equipment and woooooo it will be a hard fight with this old house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equipment pictured above:&lt;br&gt;
Unifi Dream Machine Pro&lt;br&gt;
Unifi PoE switch&lt;br&gt;
AmpliFi HD Mesh&lt;br&gt;
Echogear 20u open rack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently using AmpliFi to create a mesh while I wait for access points for the UDM Pro. Then I’ll just use it as a backup and store it, or see if I can set it up for my daughter's apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also see my stack of ThinkCenter tinys and my Raspberry Pi cluster. I actually plan to rack the Raspberry Pis with a mount I found made for them (either 1u for three or 3u for sideways mounting around 12-15). Not sure how I’m going to arrange the ThinkCenters yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also see my tiny little pihole dns servers in their neon green cases. I love the Pi Zero form factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case I didn’t bring it up before the raspberry pi 4s are for a Kubernetes cluster which will be for continuous learning and experiments, but also to run some custom apps I’m building for my home. And the ThinkCenters are for a Proxmox cluster for vms, experiments, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="homelab"></category><category term="homelab"></category><category term="networking"></category></entry><entry><title>Temperature and Humidity Sensors (part one)</title><link href="https://thebouv.com/temperature-and-humidity-sensors-part-one.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-03-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Anthony Bouvier</name></author><id>tag:thebouv.com,2021-03-18:/temperature-and-humidity-sensors-part-one.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a home from 1914 which has a lot of charm and a lot of issues. One of which is the need to constantly pay attention to the humidity levels and temperature in all floors, finished and unfinished, in the house. This project of my homelab will cover the hardware and custom software I write for it.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Setting Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a home from 1914 which has a lot of charm and a lot of issues. One of which is the need to constantly pay attention to the humidity levels and temperature in all floors, finished and unfinished, in the house. This project of my homelab will cover the hardware and custom software I write for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hardware&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4x Raspberry Pi Zero WH (just like the W, but with pre-soldered headers on the GPIO)&lt;br&gt;
4x Raspberry Pi official zero w cases&lt;br&gt;
4x Raspberry Pi official power supplies&lt;br&gt;
4x Gigastone 16gb MicroSDHC  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Operating System&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I wish I could use Ubuntu LTS on the Pi Zero W, it doesn't seem to be supported or I at least haven't been able to find out how to boot it. Like my pihole project for the lab, I'm using the most recent official Raspberry Pi OS Lite (because I don't want a desktop environment on this headless computer). And of course I use the Raspberry Pi Imager -- it's just really convenient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I image the SD card I make a couple changes to the config.txt file on the card itself from the host machine I did the imaging from.  This is so I can set the gpu mem split and disable bluetooth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: when the Raspberry Pi imager is done it unmounts the SD card, so you'll need to plug it back in to your host machine to edit the config.txt file.  On my Mac, it mounts as &lt;em&gt;boot&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I add these two lines config.txt. There are a couple of lines that already set dtoverlay that are commented out, so I just put both of these in that area:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;gpu_mem=16
dtoverlay=disable-bt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Wi-Fi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to go ahead and set up the wifi on the pi zero so that when I turn it on it automatically connects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this &lt;a href="https://learn.adafruit.com/raspberry-pi-zero-creation/text-file-editing"&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; I create the &lt;em&gt;wpa_supplicant.conf&lt;/em&gt; file on the root level of the boot drive while the SD is still connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;SSH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SSH is disabled by default so since I want to log in soon after booting it and stay headless, I merely need to add a blank file named &lt;em&gt;ssh&lt;/em&gt; to the root level of the ssd that I still have mounted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I've done that I eject the SD card and install it into the pi zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First Boot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I first boot, I want to make sure to make some changes to each device. There's probably a way to get fancy and make this super repeatable, but I'm not installing 100 sensors; I'm installing 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wrap Up Setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find the device on my network by looking at my Unifi OS that shows the whole network as a map and I just found the device and ip there, but I could also scan the network from the command line and look for Raspberry Pi MAC addresses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;arp -a | grep -i &amp;quot;b8:27:eb\|dc:a6:32&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or if you're on a Mac or a Windows machine that has Bonjour set up you might be able to talk to it at its default hostname on .local via &lt;em&gt;raspberrypi.local&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh pi@ip.address.you.found
# or 
ssh pi@raspberrypi.local
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WARNING: If you use ssh pi@raspberrypi.local more than once because you're setting up multiple sensors, keep in mind ssh is going to complain that raspberrypi.local doesn't match the fingerprint from the last time you did it. Cause each device you set up is unique, but ssh doesn't know that. So I suggest using the IP because it is more likely to be different. And below we're giving each their own hostname anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change the default password (always a smart thing to do):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;passwd
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update apt and upgrade the OS packages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; sudo apt upgrade -y
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update the hostname. I'm going with a naming scheme of 'temphum1', 'temphum2', etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo vi /etc/hostname
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now let's shut it down for now because we're going to be installing the sensor and doing some soldering next before we turn this device back on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The part two of this post will be abour the physical aspects of the project like testing out on a breadboard and soldering the real thing together.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="homelab"></category><category term="homelab"></category><category term="raspberrypi"></category></entry></feed>